{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A National company in this industry was founded by Henry “Judge” Moore. Its not in the financial industry, but a man named Charles Schwab founded a company in this industry named for Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. The largest of these companies was founded by J.P. Morgan from a company once owned by a Scottish entrepreneur who wrote “The Gospel of Wealth.” For ten points, name this industry whose largest company is named “U.S. [this]” and was originally formed by Andrew Carnegie.",
      "answer": "steel industry"
    },
    {
      "question": "This goddess’s control of the southern part of an island was confirmed after she attacked another goddess’ snow mantle during a sledding competition. This goddess’ sister Namaka flooded the holes she dug in an attempt to find a home; this goddess eventually took up residence in the Navel of the World. This daughter of Haumea and Wakea names a type of glass strand ejected from underground. For ten points, name this Polynesian fire goddess who lives in Mauna Loa and who, mythologically, created the Hawaiian Islands.",
      "answer": "Pele"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1969, this man, along with Ralph Abernathy and Walter Mondale, led marches through the Coachella Valley against illegal immigration. Philip Vera Cruz resigned from this man’s organization after this man endorsed Ferdinand Marcos. This man’s Proposition 14 was defeated, but he did successfully lead the Delano Strike. March 31st is the namesake holiday of this man whose phrase “Si, se puede” [pway-day] inspired “Yes I can,” President Obama’s slogan. For ten points, name this co-founder, with Dolores Huerta, of the United Farm Workers union.",
      "answer": "C´esar Estrada Ch´avez"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “new” version of this study was pioneered by a man who humiliated Adriaan van Roomen in a problem-solving challenge, Franciscus Vieta. The earliest instance of this discipline was found on the Strassburg tablet. Jean-Robert Argand published the first rigorous proof for the fundamental theorem of this discipline in 1814. This discipline’s name was coined by a scholar in the House of Wisdom, al-Khwarizmi. For ten points, name this branch of mathematics that involves manipulating and solving equations.",
      "answer": "algebra"
    },
    {
      "question": "Haci I Giray founded a state in this region that gained nominal independence in the Treaty of Kuchuk Kainarji. Alfonso La Marmora and Aimable P´elissier fought together in a campaign in this region. A year later in this region, Pavel Liprandi’s forces retreated, thinking that a large force lay behind Colin Campbell’s 93rd Regiment, which had formed the “thin red line.” The Siege of Sevastopol was interrupted by the Battle of Balaclava in an 1850s war named for this region. For ten points, name this peninsula that juts into the Black Sea.",
      "answer": [
        "Crimean peninsula or Tauris",
        "Tauric peninsula",
        "Crimean Khanate",
        "Crimean War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A November 2015 book about this policy noted how it was primarily formulated by rocket engineers. This policy led to creation of a group of “black” individuals who could not receive education or health care services. The “4-2-1” problem was created by this policy, which also led to the phenomenon of “little emperors.” This policy exacerbated the use of sex-selective abortions in the country where it was enacted, leading to an excess of over 30 million males. For ten points, name this policy which limited births in China until 2015.",
      "answer": "One Child Policy"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle’s preliminaires, either Daniel Wells or Henry McComas may have killed General Robert Ross. This battle was launched in response to destruction of property along Lake Erie, and was preceded by fighting at Hampstead Hill and North Point. Mary Pickersgill created one object used at this battle’s end. The song “To Anacreon in Heaven” supplied the melody for a work about this battle. For ten points, name this battle that inspired Francis Scott Key to write “The Star Spangled Banner.”",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Fort McHenry or Siege of Fort McHenry",
        "Battle of North Point before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Upon winning a game in this sport, Vitas Gerulaitis noted that “nobody beats Vitas Gerulaitis 17 times in a row!” In 2016, Raymond Moore, a tournament director in this sport, resigned after saying that women in this sport “are very, very lucky” to “ride on the coattails” of its men. In 2007, the final major championship of this sport announced gender pay equity; that championship is held at the All-England Club. For ten points, name this sport played at Wimbledon by Serena Williams and Roger Federer.",
      "answer": "tennis"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, Scott O’Grady was rescued after being shot down while maintaining a no-fly-zone in Operation Deny Flight. One side in this war was supported by the White Eagles and Arkan’s Tigers. The Heliodrom prisoner camp was set up in this war, in which Operation Storm became the largest European battle since World War II. Under the leadership of Ratko Mladic [m’lah-ditch], the VRS and the Scorpions perpetrated the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-nee-tzah] massacre in this war. The Dayton Peace Accords ended, for ten points, what 1992-95 Yugoslavian war that broke out after an independent country was established at Sarajevo?",
      "answer": "Bosnian War"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler’s daughter Enheduanna wrote a religious work titled The Exaltation of Inanna. The birth legend of this leader, who defeated king Lugal-Zage-Si of Umma, has been compared to that of Moses. This former servant of Ur-Zababa had his troops wash their weapons in the ocean to symbolize one of his conquests. This former cupbearer took control of Kish, Lagash, and Uruk to become the first emperor. For ten points, name this founder of the Akkadian Empire.",
      "answer": "Sargon the Great"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was injured when his guard misthrew a grenade, hitting a wall and falling in front of him. That action came after this man and his son, Mutassim, crawled threw a drainage pipe to escape an attacked convoy. This man’s body was showcased in a freezer in Misrata, and a cell phone video depicts people stabbing a bayonet into his rear end. This man’s murder was lamented by Mahmoud Jibril, who wished to see him tried for crimes against humanity. For ten points, name this leader who was killed in October 2011 after the National Transitional Council won a civil war against this man’s regime in Libya.",
        "answer": "Muammar Gaddafi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gaddafi’s failed escape convoy tried to get him out of this Libyan city, his birthplace.",
        "answer": "Sirte"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Harold MacMillan reacted to being snubbed by Charles de Gaulle by changing the name of this brand. Andre Turcat served as a tester for this brand. One of these vehicles suffered an accident in Gonesse that killed over one hundred people; that accident in 2000 involved a tire punctured by debris on the ground. The Tupolev Tu-144 was the only competitor to this vehicle, which stopped operations in 2003. The slogan was “Arrive before you leave” was used by, for ten points, what defunct supersonic passenger jet service?",
        "answer": "Concorde"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Concorde was flown by British Airways and this other airline, which suffered the aforementioned accident in 2000.",
        "answer": "Air France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These things are most associated with Aleksandr Afanasyev in Russia, and they are often labelled with the Aarne-Thompson classification system. One collection of these things was banned by Allied forces occupying Germany after World War II. Vladimir Propp divided their plots into 31 functions and 7 dramatis personae. A notable Freudian interpretation of one of these things interprets spilled wine and a red cloak as indicating loss of sexual innocence. For ten points, name these short stories collected by the Brothers Grimm.",
        "answer": [
          "fairy tales",
          "folk tales and other similar descriptions",
          "be lenient"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Grimm’s fairy tales is the “Town Musicians of [this city]”, which has adopted the four animals in the story as one of its symbols. This northern German city was, with Hamburg and Lu¨beck, one of the last Hanseatic cities.",
        "answer": "Free Hanseatic City of Bremen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man represented the papacy in Scandinavia, where he founded Hamar as one of five dioceses in Norway. This man died before he could excommunicate Frederick Barbarossa, and supposedly died by choking on a fly in his wine. He gave Henry II the approval to invade Ireland with the papal bull Laudabiliter. This man saw Manuel I’s invasion of southern Italy as a chance for an alliance between the Catholic Church and the Orthodox Church, which ended when the Byzantines were defeated at Brundisi. For ten points, name this pope, born Nicholas Breakspear, the only English pope.",
        "answer": [
          "Hadrian IV or Adrian IV",
          "Nicholas Breakspear before it is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Byzantine invasion of Italy, Hadrian IV tried to ally with the Byzantines, who were then led by Manuel I, a member of what family that also included Anna and Alexius?",
        "answer": [
          "Comnenus family",
          "Komnenos",
          "Comneni",
          "or Komnenoi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the Spanish-American War, John Parker’s use of this weapon earned him the nickname [this weapon] Parker. Henry Raymond used one of these weapons to defend The New York Times during the New York anti-draft riots. The creator of this weapon stated if I could “enable one man to do as much battle duty as a hundred” it would “supersede the necessity of large armies.” This weapon inspired the creation of “rotary cannons” which include the M61 Vulcan. For ten points, name this popular Civil War weapon, named for its creator, which fired bullets as fast as a soldier could crank the handle.",
        "answer": "Gatling Gun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The M61 Vulcan was developed by this company, whose refrigerator division suffered in sales by minor boycotts against its work on nuclear weapon development.",
        "answer": [
          "General Electric",
          "GE"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Abdul ibn Baz authorized the use of deadly force in this event against his former students. Christian Proteau helped plan the response to this event, whose perpetrators were charged with “misidentifying the Mahdi.” This event was carried out by members of the Ikhwan militia under Juhayman al-Otaibi, and King Khaled caved to their demands rather than crack down on extremism. The perpetrators of this event called for the overthrow of the House of Saud. For ten points, name this 1979 event that began when extremists seized the Mecca complex housing the Kaaba.",
        "answer": [
          "raid of the Grand Mosque",
          "alternatives like “seizure” instead of “raid”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Three members of the GIGN, this country’s special forces and counter-terrorism unit, advised the raid on the Grand Mosque.",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the bottom center of one of this man’s paintings, a tanned, bearded man lies against a woman to his left, who lays her head on her arm on his right shoulder. That painting by this man depicts two women chained and one dead with a baby suckling at her breast on its right; those three figures are below a rearing horseman in black wearing a turban. In another painting, this man showed a man wearing a top hat holding a musket and a boy with two pistols standing on either side of a bare breasted woman waving a tricolor and leading a charge. For ten points, name this painter of Massacre at Chios and Liberty Leading the People.",
        "answer": "Ferdinand Victor Eug`ene Delacroix"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Delacroix work about the Greek War of Independence features Greece Expiring on this place, where Lord Byron died.",
        "answer": "the ruins of Missolonghi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these people orchestrated a coup to exile a leader to Ropsha, a manor that was then given to that person. The size of this group of people prompted the nickname “Messalina on the Neva.” One of these people lost this status shortly after the Kosciuszko Uprising, and another of these people legendarily built mock villages along the Dnieper River to impress a certain somebody on her visit to Crimea. For ten points, name these men, such as Grigory Orlov and Grigory Potemkin, who had an amorous relationship with a “Great” empress of Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "lovers of Catherine the Great",
          "Catherine II for Catherine the Great",
          "just Catherine after it’s read",
          "synonyms for lovers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Grigory Potemkin is the namesake of a ship that revolted in 1905 over maggot-ridden meat, whose mutiny was chronicled by what director?",
        "answer": "Sergei Eisenstein"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1996, two civilian airplanes dispersing advocacy fliers over this country were shot down by a MiG-29, causing Madeline Albright to respond “This is not cojones [co-HO-nays], this is cowardice.” Those planes belonged to Brothers to the Rescue, whose chief goal is to aid refugees from this country. In summer 1980, citizens of this country fled it in a mass exodus called the Mariel Boatlift. For ten points, name this country, the source of many “raft refugees” who head 90 miles north to Florida.",
        "answer": "Cuba"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2000, this seven-year-old boy was returned to Cuba after the Supreme Court declined to hear his highly-publicized petition for asylum.",
        "answer": "Elian Gonzalez"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This goddess was the older figure honored in a festival in which married Athenian women traveled out of town for three days and worshipped Kalligeneia. Pigs were sacrificed at that summer festival, which honored this goddess and her child. This goddess’s “descent,” “search,” and “ascent” were the subject of the Eleusinian Mysteries, a ritual focused on this goddess’s search for her daughter, who had been kidnapped by Hades. For ten points, name this mother of Persephone, the Greek goddess of the harvest.",
        "answer": "Demeter"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This is the aforementioned summer festival honoring Demeter and Persephone. An extant Aristophanes play parodies, but does not really tell us anything about, this festival – after all, men weren’t allowed in.",
        "answer": [
          "Thesmophoria",
          "Thesmophoriazusae"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE BEAR FLAG REPUBLIC",
      "prompt": "Who or what in the Bear Flag Republic was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "current U.S. state in which it was centered near San Francisco Bay?",
          "answer": "California"
        },
        {
          "question": "country from which the republic declared its independence?",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "surname shared by the designer of the flag and his cousin Mary, the wife of Abraham Lincoln?",
          "answer": "Todd"
        },
        {
          "question": "man whose fort was used by Osos and at whose mill gold was discovered 3 years later?",
          "answer": "John Sutter"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. Army Captain who led the forces of the Bear Flag Republic?",
          "answer": "John Charles Fr´emont"
        },
        {
          "question": "city in which the Bear Flag was initially raised and then replaced with the U.S. flag a month later?",
          "answer": "Sonoma"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. ship whose Marines seized the republic?",
          "answer": "U.S.S. Portsmouth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mormon leader who proclaimed the republic?",
          "answer": "William Brown Ide MARIA THERESA"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Maria Theresa...",
      "prompt": "Name the maria theresa......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "was a member of what powerful European family, which ruled the Holy Roman Empire for three centuries?",
          "answer": "Habsburgs"
        },
        {
          "question": "sparked what 1740 to 1748 war supposedly over whether she could inherit the throne?",
          "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
        },
        {
          "question": "was unable to inherit the throne due to the law of what Frankish people?",
          "answer": "Salians or Salic Law"
        },
        {
          "question": "was allowed to succeed to the throne by her father Charles VI with what document?",
          "answer": "Pragmatic Sanction"
        },
        {
          "question": "sawwhatproductiveprovinceofherrealminvadedbyFredericktheGreat,sparkingtheaforementioned war?",
          "answer": "Silesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "was succeeded by what ruler, whose forces decimated themselves at the Battle of Karansebes?",
          "answer": "Joseph II"
        },
        {
          "question": "allied with France rather than Britain in the “reversal of alliances” in what 1756 event?",
          "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "sponsored what physician who tried to dispel superstitions about vampires, among other educational reforms?",
          "answer": "Gerard van Swieten"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CECIL RHODES",
      "prompt": "In the life of Cecil Rhodes, what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "British university to which he funded the international Rhodes scholarship?",
          "answer": "Oxford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "precious gemstone in which he made his fortune?",
          "answer": "diamond"
        },
        {
          "question": "company he founded which is still the world’s largest in said industry?",
          "answer": "De Beers"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African city that was center of his business and home to the Big Hole mine?",
          "answer": "Kimberley"
        },
        {
          "question": "German banking company that financed his early expeditions?",
          "answer": "Rothschild"
        },
        {
          "question": "insurrection he sponsored that instigated the Second Boer War?",
          "answer": "Jameson Raid"
        },
        {
          "question": "nickname for his planned but uncompleted transcontinental African railway?",
          "answer": "Cape to Cairo"
        },
        {
          "question": "mineral-rich central African region he lost to Leopold II in the Stairs Expedition?",
          "answer": "Katanga"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To deceive enemy forces into believing this group had not yet retreated, William Scurry invented a self-firing rifle that fired once cans had filled with dripping water. This group encountered fierce resistance on Lone Pine Hill on the 400 Plateau. Future historian (20 pts)",
        "Charles Bean reported on the fighting encountered after this group made an amphibious landing at a cove now named for them. A holiday named in remembrance of this group occurs on April (10 pts)",
        "25, during which sprigs of rosemary are worn and the Last Post is played. For ten points, name this group comprised of soldiers from two “down under” British dominions, who fought bravely at Gallipoli."
      ],
      "answer": "Australian and New Zealand Army Corps"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Harold Kuhn named an algorithm to solve the assignment problem after this nation, in honor of K˝onig and Egerv´ary. With Oskar Morganstern, another man from this country initialized game theory. This nation’s mathematical society bears the name of a countryman who developed non-Euclidean geometry independently of (20 pts)",
        "Nikolai Lobachevsky. A twentieth century mathematician from this country published works with over 500 (10 pts)",
        "co-authors, inspiring a namesake number as the distance on a collaboration graph. For ten points, name this nation of John von Neumann, J´anos [YAHN-osh] Bolyai, and Paul Erd˝os [AIR-dish]."
      ],
      "answer": "Hungary or Magyarorsz´ag"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This company’s status as a “natural monopoly” was weakened by a 1956 court case allowing third party providers to attach to this company’s devices. News articles regularly appear about how some customers, particularly the elderly, still (20 pts)",
        "lease this company’s devices. William Shockley’s invention of the transistor occurred at a laboratory owned by this company, which was (10 pts)",
        "broken up in the 1980s into seven “Regional Operating Companies;” in 2005, one of those companies, Southwestern Bell, took on this company’s name again. For ten points, name this largest US landline phone company."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "AT&T Corporation or Bell Telephone Company",
        "American Telephone & Telegraph",
        "Bell Labs"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A painting of this city by Henri-Paul Motte depicts men walking alongside a seawall constructed by Clement Metezeau. This city was defeated by the fleet of Henry Montmorency when it attempted to aid the revolt of the Duke of Soubise. A treaty named for this city was alternatively known as the Edict of (20 pts)",
        "Bolougne and restricted Calvinist influence to Nimes, Moutaban, and this city. One group was allowed to keep this fortress in the “Secret Articles” of the Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "Nantes. During the reign of Louis XIII, this fort was successfully besieged by Cardinal Richelieu. For ten points, name this seaport on the Bay of Biscay, a stronghold for the Huguenots."
      ],
      "answer": "La Rochelle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This deity swore her husband, Shantanu, to never question her actions, then killed each of their first seven children in an attempt to protect them from a curse. A 7th century bas-relief monument on the Coromandel Coast depicts this deity landing on Shiva’s hair during her (20 pts)",
        "descent to Earth. This deity personifies a location where drops of amrita inspired four pilgrimage sites that are visited in a (10 pts)",
        "12-year cycle. Millions of people undertake the Kumbh Mela, a pilgrimage to, for ten points, what sacred river into which the ashes of deceased Hindus are scattered?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ganges River or Ganga"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group is currently led by Scott Allen and produced “Shadow Campus” in 2014. This team’s most famous work involved an awkward front porch conversation with Ronald Paquin and helped bring about the ouster of Bernard Law. An investigation led by this group’s then-editor (20 pts)",
        "Walter Robinson included stories by Michael Rezendes and resulted in over 600 stories being published about (10 pts)",
        "sexual abuse within the Catholic Church. For ten points, name this team of investigated journalists at the Boston Globe, the subjects of a namesake 2015 film."
      ],
      "answer": "Spotlight team"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This treaty was violated in the Lisbon Incident. This treaty prompted the “Finnish War,” and one side gave up the Ionian Islands and Kotor in exchange for aid against the Ottoman Empire. The Free City of (20 pts)",
        "Danzig and Duchy of Warsaw were recognized in this treaty. The Battle of Friedland prompted this treaty, which was reversed by a French invasion in 1812. This treaty was signed on the (10 pts)",
        "Neman River when two emperors met on rafts. For ten points, name this treaty that forced Russia into joining the Continental System against Great Britain."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty of Tilsit"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Henry Campbell-Bannerman called these places “methods of barbarism” in response to the rhetorical question “When is a war not a war?” A photo taken at one of these locations shows an emaciated Lizzie van Zyl, whose eventual death was used by Emily (20 pts)",
        "Hobhouse to protest conditions in these places. A commission headed by Millicent Fawcett condemned these places, whose population grew dramatically after Lord (10 pts)",
        "Kitchener started using a scorched earth strategy. For ten points, name these locations used by the British to hold civilians during the Second Boer War, whose name was later used to describe similar facilities during the Holocaust."
      ],
      "answer": "concentration camps or internment camps"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure joined the Millerite movement after saying “The Spirit calls me, and I must go;” but departed after Jesus failed to return as predicted. One work associated with this figure was later adapted by Frances Gage, who changed the (20 pts)",
        "dialect even though the first language of the work’s creator was Dutch. This figure noted that “man is...surely between a hawk and a buzzard” because “the poor slave is on him, (10 pts)",
        "woman is coming on him;” that speech by this figure noted that the speaker had “as much muscle as any man.” For ten points, name this abolitionist and women’s rights activist who gave the “Ain’t I a Woman” speech."
      ],
      "answer": "Sojourner Truth or Isabell Baumfree"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A city of this name was taken from Gorgas by his brother Oenislus, who proceeded to assault nearby Amanthus. A statesman considered that a prophecy about this place called it “merciless,” rather than “divine,” and used income from Laurium to build “bulwarks of (20 pts)",
        "wood” that he stored on this island. At a battle named for this location, Artemisia of Halicarnassus fought bravely for a king (10 pts)",
        "watching from Mt. Aigaleo; that king was disappointed, as freshly-rested men crushed his exhausted rowers, whose ships had entered a trap set by Themistocles. For ten points, give this name shared by a decisive naval defeat for Xerxes the Great in 480 BC."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Salamis",
        "Battle of Salamis"
      ]
    }
  ]
}